Hey everyone, I've got another quick
footnote for you between chapters today.
When I've talked about linear
transformation so far, I've only really
talked about transformations from 2D
vectors to other 2D vectors represented
with 2 by 2 matrices or from 3D vectors
to other 3D vectors represented with 3
by 3 matrices.
But several commenters have asked about
non-square matrices, so I thought I'd
take a moment to just show what those
mean geometrically.
By now in the series, you actually have
most of the background you need to start
pondering a question like this on your
own, but I'll start talking through it
just to give a little mental momentum.
It's perfectly reasonable to talk about
transformations between dimensions, such
as one that takes 2D vectors to 3D
vectors. Again, what makes one of these
linear is that grid lines remain
parallel and evenly spaced and that the
origin maps to the origin.
What I have pictured here is the input
space on the left, which is just 2D
space, and the output of the
transformation shown on the right.
The reason I'm not showing the inputs
move over to the outputs like I usually
do is not just animation laziness. It's
worth emphasizing that 2D vector inputs
are very different animals from these 3D
vector outputs living in a completely
separate unconnected space.
Encoding one of these transformations
with a matrix is really just the same
thing as what we've done before. You
look at where each basis vector lands
and write the coordinates of the landing
spots as the columns of a matrix. For
example, what you're looking at here is
an output of a transformation that takes
I hat to the coordinates 2 -1 -2 and J
hat to the coordinates 0 1 1.
Notice, this means the matrix encoding
our transformation has three rows and
two columns, which to use standard
terminology makes it a 3 by 2 matrix.
In the language of last video, the
column space of this matrix, the place
where all the vectors land, is a 2D
plane slicing through the origin of 3D
space.
But the matrix is still full rank since
the number of dimensions in this column
space is the same as the number of
dimensions of the input space.
So, if you see a 3 by 2 matrix out in
the wild, you can know that it has the
geometric interpretation of mapping two
dimensions to three dimensions since the
two columns indicate that the input
space has two basis vectors and the
three rows indicate that the landing
spots for each of those basis vectors is
described with three separate
coordinates.
Likewise, if you see a 2 by 3 matrix
with two rows and three columns, what do
you think that means?
Well, the three columns indicate that
you're starting in a space that has
three basis vectors, so we're starting
in three dimensions. And the two rows
indicate that the landing spot for each
of those three basis vectors is
described with only two coordinates, so
they must be landing in two dimensions.
So, it's a transformation from 3D space
onto the 2D plane.
A transformation that should feel very
uncomfortable if you imagine going
through it.
You could also have a transformation
from two dimensions to one dimension.
One-dimensional space is really just the
number line, so a transformation like
this takes in 2D vectors and spits out
numbers.
Thinking about grid lines remaining
parallel and evenly spaced is a little
bit messy due to all of the
squishification happening here. So, in
this case, the visual understanding for
what linearity means is that if you have
a line of evenly spaced dots, it would
remain evenly spaced once they're mapped
onto the number line.
One of these transformations is encoded
with a 1 by 2 matrix, each of whose two
columns has just a single entry. The two
columns represent where the basis
vectors land and each one of those
columns requires just one number, the
number that that basis vector landed on.
This is actually a surprisingly
meaningful type of transformation with
close ties to the dot product and I'll
be talking about that next video.
Until then, I encourage you to play
around with this idea on your own
contemplating the meanings of things
like matrix multiplication and linear
systems of equations in the context of
transformations between different
dimensions. Have fun.